<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>In progress...</title>
    <description>Math and computing for the artistically inclined</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 19:45:02 -0500</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2018 19:45:02 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.7.3</generator>
    
    
      <item>
        <title>First Post!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Hello! Welcome to my site. This is a very new experience for me, and especially in the early days of this site it’ll probably be all over the place as I figure out what I want it to become. Right now I’m leaning towards showcasing the intersection of math and computer science with art (in all its forms), which probably means it’ll be me making some stuff I think is cool and then sharing it. I hope it will give others ideas for fun stuff they can do and also serve as a motivation for me to actually act on all my ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am currently interning at the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory outside Chicago, IL, where I am part of the Dark Energy Survey (DES) and the Computing Division. Last year, the first optical counterpart of a gravitational wave event was observed by the DES team, and since we expect the number of events to increase almost tenfold in the next observational run, the hope is that I will make the image processing pipeline ten times faster over these twelve weeks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime, I’ll do my best to keep updating this site! Thanks for stopping by!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 10:26:16 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/04/first-post.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/jekyll/update/2018/06/04/first-post.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>jekyll</category>
        
        <category>update</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
